Register of the Daniel Lerner collection
Hoover Institution Archives
Daniel Lerner collection
1914-1949
46019
Hoover Institution Archives
87 manuscript boxes, 1 envelope (36.4 linear feet)
Reports, correspondence, pamphlets, leaflets, and radio transcripts relating to Allied propaganda in Europe during World War II, analysis of German propaganda, evaluation of wartime German morale, and German public opinion during the post-war Allied occupation. Includes reports of interrogations of German prisoners of war.
Lerner, Daniel, 1917-, collector
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1946.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
Daniel Lerner (1917-1980), author and professor of sociology, worked as Chief Editor of the Psychological Warfare Division, SHAEF (1944-1945) and as Chief of Intelligence of the Information Control Division, OMGUS (1945-1946).
Scope and Content Note
Daniel Lerner gathered a portion of the collection in 1944-1945 when he worked as Chief Editor of the Psychological Warfare Division, SHAEF (1944-1945), and as Chief of Intelligence of the Information Control Division, OMGUS (1945-1946). He supplemented the collection with materials he found during his two trips to Europe in 1946 to 1947 and in 1948 while he was Research Director of the International Studies Center at the Hoover Institution of Stanford University. Lerner's book, entitled Sykewar: Psychological Warfare against Germany (New York: George W. Stewart, 1949), is partially based on the collection materials.
Germany--History--1945-1955.; Germany.; Prisoners of war.; Propaganda.; Public opinion--Germany.; World War, 1939-1945--Germany.; World War, 1939-1945--Prisoners and prisons.; World War, 1939-1945--Propaganda.; World War, 1939-1945--Psychological aspects.; World War, 1939-1945.
- Captured German Documents, 1944-1945 (Boxes 1-9)
  Scope and Contents note
  Administrative orders, clippings, correspondence, diaries, instructions, leaflets, maps, memoranda, pamphlets, reports. The series includes only those German documents that were processed by various agencies of American and British governments and forwarded to the Psychological Warfare Division. The original arrangement—division into files A, DE, etc.—has been preserved, although the reasons for such a division are not always clear. Copies of the same document may sometimes be found in several files. The inventories of three files (DE, PID, and S) were compiled previously, perhaps by Daniel Lerner. Two of them (DE and S) appear in Lerner's book, Sykewar: Psychological Warfare against Germany, pp. 350-389. Although a few documents in these files are missing, the inventories were incorporated in the register unchanged
  - General (Folder 1: 1)
    - Memorandum on subversive activities of Russians in the German army, (unnumbered), June 1944
    - Memorandum on political tasks of the German soldier in the East, (unnumbered), 18 October 1944
    - Memorandum on morale in the Wehrmacht, (unnumbered), 27 October 1944
    - Directives to use Allied decrees in occupied Germany for stirring up hatred against the Allies, (unnumbered), November 1944
    - Thirty-eight extracts from letters written by German civilians, (#344), October 1944-January 1945
    - Ten extracts from letters written by German civilians, (#345), October 1944 - November 1945
    - Directives for Nationalsozialistische Führungsoffiziere (NSFOs) (#347)
    - Directives for NSFOs (#349)
    - Directives for NSFOs, (#350), February 1945
    - Leaflet on communication among drivers during air raids, (#352), n.d.
    - Four extracts from letters written by German civilians and soldiers, (#353), August-November 1944
    - Diary of a NSFO, (#360), July 1944 - February 1945
    - Eleven extracts from letters written by German civilians and soldiers, (#370), March 1945
    - Three extracts from German newssheets, (#371), March-April 1945
  - A-File (Folder 1: 2)
    - Report on sanitary conditions among German front line troops, (#266), July 1944
    - Himmler's order: Germans should work and fight even harder, (#331), 2 August 1944
    - Three letters to civilians and extracts from a diary by a soldier on difficulties of war conditions, (#361), May-September 1944
    - Instruction concerning organization and equipment of the Volkssturm, (#627), November 1944
    - German leaflet on success of German troops, (#679), November-December 1944
    - Report on conditions in the concentration camp Dachau by a German who was put for an indefinite term in Dachau for "his repeated ignoring of order to work on a road-building project" in (#798), June 1937
    - Six extracts from letters written by soldiers and civilians in Germany, (#1522), 1944-1945
    - Extracts from interrogation reports of German POWs on their attitude toward Americans and Russians, and memorandum on furloughs for German soldiers from the East (#1580)
    - Extracts from three letters from Berlin area addressed to a German soldier captured in Alsace, (#1603), January-February 1945
    - Seven extracts from letters by German civilians to soldiers, (#1608), January-February 1945
    - Extracts from six letters by German civilians and soldiers, (#1675), January-February 1945
    - Extracts from nine letters written by German civilians to soldiers, (#1830), February 1945
    - German propaganda materials, (#1831), February-March 1945
    - Messages by Himmler and Jodl on necessity to fight to the last soldier,, and information given by a foreign worker on a new location of the propaganda radio station "Siegfried Line Calling" (#1864), April 1945
    - Two extracts from a letter written by a German civilian to a soldier, (#1876), March 1945
    - NSDAP propaganda materials. Instructions and leaflets (#1924)
    - Reports by Sicherheitsdienst (SD) in Aschaffenburg concerning morale of the population, (#1925), December 1944 - February 1945
    - Propaganda directives to German newspapers,, and a letter to Eisenhower signed by women of Heidelberg (#1926), March 1945
    - Letter signed by Eduard Schneider to the American military government; SS order on curfew,; propaganda leaflets on Werwolf and on Hitlerjugend in the Volkssturm (#1927), April 1945
  - DE-File (Folder 1: 3)
    - Ten extracts from letters written by German civilians (#9)
    - "High treason" of German prisoners of war. Threats against their families (#10)
    - Diary of life in the "Etappe" (#11)
    - Handbook and maps for the invasion of Great Britain (#12)
    - Communications for the troops (#13)
    - More strength through fear and more social demagogy (#14)
    - Replacements for German units must be "infiltrated" with Nazi spirit (#15)
    - The Führer's order to hold battle line to the last man (#16)
    - German propaganda in the North-West (#17)
    - Troops reproved (#17-A)
    - Diary of SS-Rottenführer, H. Pueker (Hitler plot, Himmler, listening to BBC) (#19)
    - Warnings against looting and desertions (#20)
    - More threats against deserters (#21)
    - Parts of Volksgrenadier Division "beat it." Renewed threats of shooting (#22)
    - Plundering by German troops in Reich territory (#23)
    - Wounded German soldiers "unreliable" (#24)
    - Order against continued rumors about treachery of German officers (#25)
    - Punishment threat to German soldiers found in possession of "red safe-conduct" (#26)
    - Diary of experiences of German soldier Erich Heutschel (#27)
    - Diary of German Hitler youth (#28)
    - Diary extract re disobedience of men and cowardice of officers (#29)
    - "Die Geheimwaffe des Feindes ist eingesetzt!" (#30)
    - German leaflet to German troops to hold Metz (#31) (Folder 1: 4)
    - Samples of Nazi propaganda to German troops (#32)
    - Sixteen extracts from letters written by German civilians (#33)
    - German leaflet for German troops (#34)
    - Three letter extracts from imprisoned wife to German soldier (#35)
    - Letter report by German schoolboy on the state funeral of Oberstleutnant Lent (#36)
    - Twelve extracts from German civilian letters (#37)
    - Five death sentences on deserters from Volksgrenadier Division (#38)
    - Twelve points for political training of German soldiers (#39)
    - Disabled and ill men called for front-line duties (#40)
    - Extracts from Gen. F.M. Model's address to German troops (#41)
    - Diary re fighting in Alsace-Lorraine and western Germany (#42)
    - Requisitioning of small arms; pros and cons of stepping up production (#43)
    - Propaganda directives for Nazi Party (#44)
    - Confidential directives for propaganda to German women (#45)
    - German Army High Command instructions for German unit leaders (extracts) (#46)
    - Leaflet for German soldiers: "Da gibt es nun wieder 2 Möglichkeiten" (#47)
    - Communications for the troops (#48-49)
    - SS leader corrects Propaganda Ministry (#50)
    - Instructions for Unit leaders; political explanation of new weapons (#51)
    - Directives for hate propaganda re Allied measures in occupied German territory (#52)
    - Extracts from "Die Lage" (#53)
    - "Hitler bears the guilt for our misery": Extract from Special Court files (#54)
    - "Quarrel over the booty" (#55)
    - Seven extracts from letters written by German soldiers (#56)
    - "Why Nazi Commissars?" (#57)
    - German propaganda leaflet to Americans: "Your near Future.. .?" (#58)
    - Model's appeal not sufficiently followed (#59)
    - Diary of Alsatian soldier serving with German Army (#61)
    - Party bureaucracy re Gen. Field Marshal v. Reichenau's widow (#62)
    - Lightning News: November Issue (#63)
    - New warning against looting by German soldiers on German territory (#64)
    - "Breach of international law by American troops" (#65) (Folder 1: 5)
    - Soldiers back civilians against evacuation order or party (#66)
    - People's Grenadier Division under personal care of Himmler (#67)
    - Nazi Commissar's complaints (#68)
    - Summary of documents re organization and equipment of the Volkssturm (#69)
    - Hate and atrocity propaganda against Allied rule (#70)
    - Gauleiter's order: "With bicycles against tanks!" (#71)
    - C.O. of German 1st Army reveals serious decline in Army's discipline (#73)
    - Orders for building new main line of resistance but material not available (#74)
    - Nazi propaganda leaflet to Allies (#75)
    - Punishment of German corporal for writing defeatist letter (#76)
    - Summarized extracts from German documents re morale, discipline (#77)
    - German leaflet for German troops: Persuasion against rumors and panic (#78)
    - Original of captured German paper "Skorpion-Informationsdienst" (#79)
    - Reaction to Allied propaganda (#80)
    - German propaganda for Germans: "Wer Kauft Gips zum Kuchenbacken?" (#81)
    - German propaganda for German troops (#82)
    - German propaganda for American troops (#83)
    - Diary of Ltn. Erich Halfpap on experiences in reserve regiment (#84)
    - German propaganda leaflet to British troops (#85)
    - Twelve extracts from German soldiers' letters (#86)
    - Hitler order to fight for Metz to the last man (#87)
    - Reaction to Allied leaflet (#88)
    - Divisional Commander criticizes Company Leaders (#89)
    - Terror poster by Nazi leader (#90)
    - Diary of German soldier (#91)
    - Kittel threatens to use artillery fire against deserters and POWs (#93)
    - Article by War Correspondent, New York Herald Tribune (#94)
    - SS explanation of defeat (#95)
    - General restrictions on foreign workers (#96)
    - Arguments of German women against "total war work" (#97)
    - Lightning News (#98)
    - Lightning News (#99)
    - Stand-and-hold leaflet distributed to German troops during middle of (#101), November 1944 (Folder 1: 6)
    - Nine extracts from German soldiers' letters (#102)
    - Directives for conduct under enemy occupation (#103)
    - Diary of Waffen-SS man (#104)
    - Daily Gestapo report (#105)
    - Extracts from letters by German girl to her parents (#106)
    - Battle-fit or slightly damaged armed vehicles and tanks not to be removed from battlefield (#107)
    - Extracts from captured German documents concerning propaganda, morale, etc. (#109)
    - Gestapo report re differences between the SS and German Army (#110)
    - Nazi propaganda leaflet for Allied troops (#111)
    - Lightning News (#112)
    - Nazi propaganda for Alsatians (#113)
    - C.O.'s order re reinforcement of defenses in the West (#114)
    - Transfer of Army technicians to U-Boat and air force duties (#115)
    - Frontier police given independent authority (#116)
    - Twelve extracts from soldiers' letters (#117)
    - Precautions against deserters (#118)
    - Ten extracts from German civilian letters (#119)
    - Diary of Romanian (Volksdeutsche) who complains about discrimination against Volksdeutsche (#120)
    - Eight extracts from letters written by German soldiers (#121)
    - Nine extracts from German civilian letters (#122)
    - Orders of the Day before the great German counteroffensive (#123)
    - Another insight into German hate propaganda (#124)
    - Economic situation in the Reich and postwar hopes (#125)
    - Fortifications in the West (#126)
    - Eleven extracts describing air raids on Graz and Salzburg, and effect on population (#127)
    - Contradictions in German statements concerning treatment of nations under Nazis (#128)
    - Eleven extracts from German soldiers' letters (#129)
    - Organization and equipment of the Volkssturm (#130)
    - Lack of coordination in 17 SS Pz. Gren. Div. (#131)
    - Activities of the Feldjäger (#132)
    - Strict measures imposed on Lorraine population near Bitsch (#133) (Folder 1: 7)
    - German war reporter on zero hour of the offensive (#134)
    - Sentence of death on Dutchman who did not obey German order to build dams (#135)
    - Gauleiter Wagner advised of urgency of building shelters in Karlsruhe (#136)
    - Mercy appeal to U.S. Commander by seven German officers and men who violated the Geneva Convention by wearing American uniforms (#137)
    - The Führer's order to await further instructions re reconstruction (#138)
    - The Führer's order re new "Front-OT" within old organization Todt (#139)
    - F. M. Model's propaganda directives to N.S. leaders (#140)
    - Eight extracts from German civilian letters (#141)
    - Passive resistance of Catholic priests in the Reich (#142)
    - Treatment of foreign workers in Germany (#143)
    - Difficulties for German transport system, caused by Allied air raids (#144)
    - German people not to be told of shortages of meat, fat, potatoes, etc. (#145)
    - Orders to hold bridgehead of Venlo; every tenth tank is to be destroyed (#146)
    - Discovery of a Polish resistance movement in Pomerania (#147)
    - Preservation of pure German blood endangered by relations between Italian workers and German women (#148)
    - No (civilian) executive powers for military commanders, only for Gauleiters (#149)
    - Eight extracts from German civilian letters (#150)
    - Orders of the Day before big German counteroffensive (#151)
    - Incorporation of Eastern volunteers in Volksgrenadier Regiment affects reliability (#152)
    - Large order placed with Berlin firm for paper to be used for leaflets (#153)
    - Slackness, etc., of communication personnel makes contact between Jäger Regiments and Artillery Liaison Detachment impossible (#154)
    - German propaganda leaflet (#155)
    - German propaganda leaflet: "Was wird?" (#156)
    - Spotlight on Regimental Commander (#157)
    - Eleven extracts from German civilian letters (#158)
    - SS Pz. Gren. Div. Troops instructed on how to behave on German territory (#159)
    - Order stressing need for not only medical, but psychological, welfare of troops (#160)
    - Search for English-speaking soldiers... for propaganda purposes (#161)
    - German instructions re POW interrogations, etc. (#162)
    - German propaganda leaflet (#163)
    - German information sheet and leaflet re behavior of troops in occupied territory (#164)
    - German propaganda leaflet for German troops (#165)
    - Model's order re technique of sleep (#166)
    - German propaganda leaflet (#167)
    - Seyss-Inquart deplores panic flight of Nazi officials from the Netherlands (#168)
    - Strange bedfellows in the Volkssturm - Retired generals and criminals (#169)
    - Keitel order curtails staff and petrol of generals and admirals (#170) (Box-folder 2: 1)
    - Nine extracts from letters written by German civilians. Two songs (#171)
    - Gauleiter reproved for haphazard selection of Volkssturm leaders (#172)
    - Recent CO order and notice re looting, etc. (#173)
    - Development of Nazi youth (#174)
    - Strict measures ordered against German deserters, etc. (#175)
    - Model's Christmas message to the troops (#176)
    - German leaflet to German troops: "Saboteur or not?" (#177)
    - Rundstedt's New Year message to the troops (#178)
    - Order of the Day by Lt. Col. v. d. Heydte on occasion of receiving oak-leaf cluster (#179)
    - Fourteen extracts from letters written by German civilians (#180)
    - Suggested formation of English Legion in Reich to fight against the Bolsheviks (#181)
    - Defeatist remarks from retreating German staff officers are bad influence on Alsatian population (#182)
    - "German tea." This ersatz commodity no longer to be dignified with the term "German" (#183)
    - Bormann takes dim view of suggestion to use POWs as protection for important installations against Allied air raids (#184)
    - German C.G.S. orders re measures for preventing documents from falling into Allied hands (#185)
    - Shortages in the German Army (#186)
    - Discipline by force of arms - "Don't wait for court martial" (#187)
    - German Army fears betrayal from within (#188)
    - Report on food situation in Reich in the sixth year of war (#189)
    - Orders to German troops re looting on Reich territory (#190)
    - Nazis fear effect of Allied propaganda on the people of Alsace, Lorraine, and Luxembourg (#191)
    - Model hopes to draw victory from defeat (#192)
    - Model's orders re lack of discipline and security-mindedness (#193)
    - Rundstedt order re lack of discipline among troops (#194)
    - Lack of discipline in SS Geb. Jg. Regt. in Oslo (#195)
    - Recent shortages in Panzer Artillery Regiment (#196)
    - Soldiers' worries in Panzer Artillery Regiment (#197)
    - Reasons for reverses in German Army in November (#198)
    - Order to cease discrimination between rear and front-line troops (#199)
    - Model reproves unit leaders for staying in the rear and not accompanying the troops (#200) (Folder 2: 2)
    - Strict measure to be taken to eliminate possible ways and means of desertion (#201)
    - Insufficient training caused by lack of equipment (#202)
    - Model orders Army vehicles to assist in evacuating German civilians (#203)
    - "Did the Führer know best?" (#204)
    - Seven extracts from soldiers' letters (#205)
    - Model's New Year message to the troops (#206)
    - The horrors of defeat. NSFO directives to troops, why they must fight on (#206A)
    - Propaganda leaflet for German troops re looting civilian population (#207)
    - He who wins the winter, wins the war (#208)
    - "J'accuse" (A good German writes to a good Nazi) (#209)
    - Battalion Commander's lament about bad shooting, poor discipline, etc. (#210)
    - Slack execution of orders, etc. (#211)
    - Extracts from "Abwehr Merkblatt, 1944," re closer attention to security (#212)
    - Eight extracts from German soldiers' letters (#213)
    - Rundstedt orders war troops against unfavorable criticism of other sections of the Army (#214)
    - "Stomach Unit men fine fighting troops!" (#215)
    - Importance of December offensive stressed to next of kin of fallen soldiers (#216)
    - "The truth about the Waffen-SS" (#217)
    - "Is your journey really necessary?" (#218)
    - German propaganda to German troops (#219)
    - Himmler's war aims (#220)
    - Commander's order to eighteen Volksgren. Div. on eve of German December offensive (#221)
    - Fourteen extracts from letters written by German civilians to soldiers at the Western Front (#222)
    - Failure of German evacuation measures in the West (#223)
    - German concern about Allied leaflets (#224)
    - German women in the war (#225)
    - Serious effect of Allied low-level attacks on German transport (#226)
    - Extracts from Army documents re desertion (#227)
    - Mahlmann order "Better Death than Slavery" (#228)
    - Sepp Dietrich's New Year message (#229)
    - Model order re plundering in German territory (#230)
    - Poor chances for the ideal Nazi bride (#231)
    - Document extracts from files of two Parachute Regiments before and after the December offensive (#232) (Folder 2: 3)
    - "No booty to the enemy!" (#233)
    - German leaflet to Allied troops, designed to sow dissension among American and French Armies fighting side by side (#234)
    - Text of German leaflet quoting the Führer's New Year Order of the Day (#235)
    - Treason, weakness, and cowardice of "Etappen" officers (#236)
    - The food situation (#237)
    - "Wozu das alles" - Nazi propaganda for wounded soldiers (#238)
    - Confidential NSFO News Sheet of the German Navy articles of (#239), 29 December 1944
    - Adolf Hitler's curriculum vitae and how to use it (#240)
    - German leaflet: The hour of decision has come" (#241)
    - Ten extracts from letters written by German civilians to soldiers (#242)
    - Sidelights on the Volkssturm (#243)
    - Food problems facing the German commander on the Atlantic coast (#244)
    - Medical officer on lack of ambulances, carelessness with medicine bottles (#245)
    - Road transport and traffic difficulties (#246)
    - Orders of Col. Kuehne to 246 VG Div. (#247)
    - NSFO directives (#248)
    - "Infantry infiltration methods" to overcome Allied material superiority (#249)
    - Attitude of civilian population in Alsace under German occupation (#250)
    - Germany's oil dilemma (#251)
    - Eleven extracts from letters by German soldiers (#253)
    - Eighty percent of all subordinate commanders are below the basic training standard of a recruit (#254)
    - Conscripts desert and soldiers on leave are attacked in Upper Silesia (#255)
    - Eleven extracts from letters written by German civilians (#256)
    - "The war won't be won until the Anglo-Americans are cleared out of Europe" (#257)
    - Main line unit seriously weakened through losses (#258)
    - Introduction of new identity card "W" in German pay books (#259)
    - "S C A N D A L S" (#260)
    - German propaganda directives (#261)
    - Extracts from an NSFO progress report (#262)
    - Our critical situation on all fronts (#263)
    - Model offers special premiums for the shooting down of Allied planes (#264)
    - Civilian population impressed by correct behavior of American troops (#265)
    - Germany's labor problem (#266)
    - NSFO February News Digest (#267)
    - Unwillingness to get at the enemy (#268)